<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The two main questions resolved how 1 the ministers 2 the impropriators shall be maintained satisfied if tythes be put down. Often petitioned for, by several counties, and propounded and debated at a meeting not far from London, by divers eminent personages of this Common-wealth, and sundry freeholders, and others, attending on them. By D. Lupton, servant of Jesus Christ in the work of the Gospel.</title>
            <author>Lupton, Donald, d. 1676.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88652</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868004</idno>
  <idno type="VID">169782</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240936709</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3494</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1331_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209104</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868004</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99868004e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88652)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169782)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 176:E1331[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The two main questions resolved how 1 the ministers 2 the impropriators shall be maintained satisfied if tythes be put down. Often petitioned for, by several counties, and propounded and debated at a meeting not far from London, by divers eminent personages of this Common-wealth, and sundry freeholders, and others, attending on them. By D. Lupton, servant of Jesus Christ in the work of the Gospel.</title>
                  <author>Lupton, Donald, d. 1676.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 27, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.W. for R. Harford, at the Bible and States-Arms in Little-Brittain,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M DC LII. [1652]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The words "The ministers .. impropriators" are bracketed together on title page, as are the words "shall be".</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "August. 12".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Tithes --  Great Britain --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169782:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Two Main</hi> QVESTIONS RESOLVED: How
<list>
                  <item>1 <hi>The Ministers</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>The Impropriators</hi>
                  </item>
               </list> shal be
<list>
                  <item>Maintained</item>
                  <item>Satisfied</item>
               </list> If <hi>TYTHES</hi> be put down.</p>
            <p>Often PETITIONED for, by several Counties, and Propounded and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated at a Meeting not far from <hi>London,</hi> by divers Eminent Personages of this Common-Wealth, and sundry Freeholders, and Others, attending on them.</p>
            <p>By <hi>D. Lupton,</hi> Servant of Jesus Christ in the work of the GOSPEL.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mat. 23.23. Luk. 11.42.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Woe unto you Scribes and Pharisees, Hypocrites, for ye Tithe Mint and Rue, and all manner of Herbs, and have omitted the weightier matters of the Law; Judgement, Mercy, and Faith.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. W.</hi> for <hi>R. Harford,</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>States-Arms</hi> in <hi>Little-Brittain,</hi> MDCLII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:169782:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169782:2"/>
            <head>How the Ministers shall be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for; if Tythes be put down?</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Ministers of <hi>England</hi> for their Annual gains, and Titular prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, (the two chief <hi>spurs</hi> and <hi>pullies</hi> to <hi>force</hi> forward, and draw on their Covetous and Ambitious Spirits) have for hundreds of yeers by plausible perswasions held out to, and made the people of <hi>England believe</hi> without the least <hi>scruple,</hi> the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Right of payment of Tythes; there were few or none who in those times for fear of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastical <hi>censures</hi> (the onely Bugbears to keep truth concealed,) durst appear to <hi>vindicate</hi> or manifest it.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:169782:3"/>
            <p> But of late (God pleasing to so order times, and <hi>the piety</hi> of our Parliament upholding <hi>truth</hi>) it hath some <hi>favor</hi> and <hi>liberty</hi> to shew its <hi>face;</hi> so that all the people of this Land may be, and (we hope) are fully satisfied, yes, and the Clergy too, <hi>fully</hi> convinced, though hardly brought unto it; That Tythes are not now, by the people of this <hi>Land,</hi> by any Divine Right to be paid unto the Ministers of the same: The sundry Petitions of several Counties already <hi>exhibited,</hi> and others who are ready to come up; with the several <hi>books</hi> and <hi>treatises</hi> of some Mens <hi>pens,</hi> though in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber not many, nor varnished over with <hi>smooth</hi> and <hi>flattering</hi> language; (for Truth <hi>desires</hi> a plain habit) and whose persons, though not great in <hi>worldly</hi> preferments (for, such who seek the <hi>discovery</hi> of truth, catch at no such <hi>shaddows</hi>) and did they, they would miss of their Aym, <hi>for the world will love her own;</hi> both these send forth <hi>strong</hi> Arguments and <hi>loud</hi> cries, for the putting of Tythes down in this Common-Wealth.</p>
            <p>And seeing that God hath pleased to <hi>enable</hi> and to <hi>choose</hi> such <hi>pens</hi> (though weak in esteem) to manifest <hi>this truth</hi> against payment of Tythes any longer; Who, of any <hi>sound</hi> Judgement, or <hi>sincere</hi> Conscience can dislike <hi>his</hi> choice? Let the Clergy (and the Impropriators, properly so cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, who side with them for gains) take heed how they strive against the truth, or endeavor to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169782:3"/>
               <hi>withhold</hi> the truth, <hi>now appearing</hi> in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar against <hi>Tyth-taking,</hi> under the Gospel; <hi>Truth</hi> is, and will be opposed, but it cannot be op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed.</p>
            <p>Tis true, manifold are the Writers for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Tythes, but their works, how <hi>flaccid</hi> and void of <hi>substantial</hi> truth? themselves are <hi>weary</hi> if not <hi>abashed</hi> at their own works: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the next place being <hi>startled</hi> with guilt and fear, they have left their <hi>pens,</hi> and use their <hi>tongues,</hi> in accusing such for <hi>unjust, unmerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, unrighteous, factious,</hi> and <hi>cruell</hi> men, who either petition, or write any thing against Tythes; and that <hi>they</hi> and their <hi>families</hi> will <hi>by this means</hi> be utterly <hi>undone;</hi> they cry out as that unjust steward did, <hi>Digg I cannot, and to beg I am ashamed.</hi> That 8. or 10000. <hi>families,</hi> who have been hitherto <hi>tenderly</hi> brought up, must now starve, and that learning must live upon <hi>Almes,</hi> and <hi>peoples</hi> charity; That such who petition a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Tythes, or <hi>write</hi> to put them down, intend <hi>to extirpate</hi> the Gospel and Preaching too: these and many such are the <hi>Clamors</hi> they <hi>raise,</hi> and these things they <hi>infuse</hi> into mens fancies (and those no small Ones neither) of our unjust in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendments.</p>
            <p>And therefore to satisfie the world, it shall <hi>appear</hi> to all Conscionable men, that we have more <hi>care</hi> of them, than they of themselves; we
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169782:4"/>hope to <hi>Reform</hi> them, is not <hi>to ruine</hi> them; to <hi>steer</hi> them, is not <hi>to starve</hi> them; to <hi>reduce</hi> them from <hi>an old error</hi> is Charity and Mercy, not Malice: to <hi>Inform</hi> them whats best, we conceive <hi>is best</hi> for them; and though there be an <hi>Alteration</hi> of their <hi>maintenance,</hi> there is not <hi>a privation.</hi> If they <hi>say,</hi> 'twill be <hi>little,</hi> or <hi>nothing</hi> to what they had by <hi>Tythes;</hi> for peoples <hi>charity</hi> they fear will be <hi>small,</hi> and quickly <hi>cold:</hi> if it <hi>should</hi> be little; they may learn <hi>content;</hi> and a little <hi>well got,</hi> is better then <hi>a great deal</hi> with the <hi>wages of unrighteous<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness.</hi> And if many of them should have <hi>little,</hi> or <hi>nothing</hi> allowed them by the State, 'twas but their <hi>due</hi> wages, for Hundreds of them do not any thing for, but rather against the Magistrate, scarce <hi>vouchsafing</hi> the Parliament, Councill of State, or our Armies either by <hi>Sea,</hi> or <hi>Land,</hi> a good word; not mentioning them in their <hi>publike</hi> Prayers, nor craving Gods blessing upon their Persons or Actions.</p>
            <p>This is true O presbyterian Ministers! And yet you do expect to have Tythes upheld by these men.</p>
            <p>If the peoples Charity be <hi>Cold,</hi> 'tis your selves are <hi>in fault;</hi> And know this, that better, more able, and holier men than you are, have lived by <hi>Charitable</hi> Collections, and thankfull too; what if you be put to it? are you <hi>better</hi> than Christ, his Apostles, and the <hi>primitive</hi> Christians?
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:169782:4"/>To come therefore to our <hi>Intendment.</hi> How our Ministers shall be <hi>provided for,</hi> if Tythes be <hi>put down?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We say, whilest we are providing <hi>for them,</hi> we hope they have no just cause to be angry with us for our <hi>Care,</hi> and <hi>good-will</hi> towards them; if they be, we know <hi>at whose</hi> dore the <hi>sin</hi> will lye; and therefore,</p>
            <p>First, may not our Ministers, nay ought they not <hi>to conform</hi> themselves and Actions; their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctise and behaviour to Christ <hi>himself,</hi> his Apostles, and to the <hi>Primitive</hi> Christians? Can they have a <hi>fairer,</hi> or <hi>surer</hi> pattern then these? or a safer <hi>Rule</hi> to walk by, than Gods word? Or, shall the Popish Dispensatory Indulgences be <hi>accounted</hi> of more <hi>worth,</hi> or <hi>necessity</hi> (and so be <hi>upheld</hi> by our Tythe-takers) than the <hi>Precepts,</hi> or <hi>Practice</hi> of Christ or his Apostles? because, by the Popes, in former times, our Tythe-takers were <hi>favoured</hi> and <hi>indulged,</hi> that so all <hi>Collations</hi> to <hi>Benefices,</hi> and <hi>first fruits</hi> of all Bishopricks and other <hi>Ecclesiasti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> places, might flow into <hi>their Coffers</hi> at Rome: for they gave Tythes to the Clergy, that they might have the profits aforesaid to themselves. Shall we <hi>imagine</hi> therefore, <hi>that they</hi> who wore the Triple Mitre, had more wit, wildom, truth, or equity in their <hi>decrees;</hi> Than <hi>he</hi> who wore a <hi>Crown of Thornes,</hi> hath in his heavenly word? Oh no!</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:169782:5"/>
               <l>—Impar Congressus</l>
            </q>
            <p>And therefote, we will <hi>describe</hi> unto all men, And specially to the Ministers of <hi>England</hi> some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of our Saviour Christ As first, <hi>his journeying.</hi> Secondly, <hi>His Apparel.</hi> Thirdly, <hi>His diet,</hi> with his <hi>manner of Maintenance</hi> while he was upon Earth Fourthly, of his Apostles and their practice. Fifthly, Of the <hi>primitive</hi> Christians and their <hi>manner</hi> of Maintenance; and we will, in the next place see whether <hi>tythe-taking</hi> by our Ministers or Impropriators <hi>will hold</hi> with their doings or not; <hi>if they speak not according to this, tis because there is no truth in them.</hi> Isaiah 8. And so we will sum up what the whole will <hi>yield</hi> for our Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in this particular.</p>
            <p>To begin therefore with his travailes, when <hi>he</hi> or his <hi>Disciples</hi> journeyed (as they did dayly, <hi>going about</hi> and <hi>doing good,</hi> even unto <hi>weariness,</hi> as we may see Joh. 4.) it was alwayes <hi>on foot,</hi> except once, and that was, when he rid into Jerusalem, rather to <hi>fulfill</hi> that prophesie of Zachary, <hi>behold thy King cometh meekly sitting upon an Ass, Zach.</hi> 9. though he did at that time <hi>ride,</hi> yet it was <hi>in meekness</hi> and <hi>lowliness</hi> of minde, and it was not two miles; and usually <hi>without shoes,</hi> onely used <hi>sandals,</hi> meetly to defend the feet from <hi>stones</hi> or pricks, or other <hi>Incumbrances,</hi> or else, when he passed some <hi>lake;</hi> not so much for ease, as to shew <hi>his diligence</hi> to be about <hi>his spiritual work,</hi> or to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169782:5"/>work Miracles <hi>on the water</hi> as he did, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9 to awaken and confirm his Disciples faith; this is enough to shew his <hi>pains</hi> and <hi>labour, patience,</hi> and <hi>humility</hi> with his followers. <hi>Behold the man;</hi> Oh <hi>Ministers!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, We proceed to speak of <hi>His apparel,</hi> his <hi>predecessor</hi> came clothed in Camels <hi>hair,</hi> and a <hi>leathern</hi> girdle <hi>about his loines,</hi> Mat. 3. and our blessed Saviour said, that they <hi>who were clothed in soft Raiment,</hi> were <hi>in Kings palaces,</hi> which <hi>he</hi> came not into, onely when he was <hi>forced</hi> thither, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26, and sent from <hi>Pilate</hi> to <hi>Herod</hi> in <hi>mockery;</hi> His apparrel was only for <hi>use,</hi> and <hi>necessity:</hi> we read not of any chests of <hi>fine linnen,</hi> or <hi>Wardrobes</hi> of rich Attire: when the Soldiers <hi>stript</hi> his clothes from his back, they took all that he <hi>at present</hi> had, and they were no costly ones neither; and when his disciples took <hi>care</hi> for <hi>temporal</hi> provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, amongst other things he counsells them, after this manner, Mat. 6. <hi>Why take ye thought for rayment; Consider the Lillies of the field;</hi> but we hasten.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Let us observe his diet, <hi>'twas his meat and drink to do his fathers will.</hi> Not that he did not eat any thing, or not <hi>drink</hi> at all, but he did it <hi>by the by,</hi> as we say: his <hi>chief</hi> intent and <hi>drift,</hi> or his <hi>onely</hi> meat and drink, was the accomplish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his fathers <hi>will.</hi> But we may <hi>gather</hi> from the word, what manner of <hi>food</hi> he used. For when
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169782:6"/>he fed 5000. people, he asked his Disciples, <hi>how many Loaves have ye?</hi> and one Answerd, <hi>five Barly Loaves and a few small fishes;</hi> Bread they had, but not of <hi>Wheat,</hi> but <hi>Barly,</hi> nor <hi>much</hi> neither, onely five Loaves, and <hi>they</hi> were not <hi>much</hi> for 13. or 14. <hi>travelling</hi> men to feed on; and when he told them, <hi>he had compassion on the Multitude,</hi> they reply, 200. peny-worth of <hi>bread</hi> will not <hi>suffice;</hi> here's only bread for the <hi>Caterer</hi> to buy, if he had gone, and doubtless it should have been of <hi>Barley,</hi> if he had bought any. He begun his Gospel with <hi>fasting and prayer,</hi> Mat. 4. often at prayer, seldom eating, <hi>Take no care what ye shall eat, or what ye shall drink</hi> Mat. 6. that rich Glutton of whom he <hi>spoke,</hi> fared <hi>deliciously</hi> every day, but he went into <hi>hell,</hi> where he wanted <hi>one drop</hi> of water. Luk. 16. when he had <hi>fed</hi> the Multitude, gave Order, <hi>to gather up the fragments,</hi> not onely because they should not be <hi>lost,</hi> but that they might be <hi>given</hi> either to the <hi>poor,</hi> or else that they might serve his <hi>Disciples</hi> to eat. And for mony, as 'tis certain he had some (for <hi>Judas</hi> kept it) yet <hi>not much;</hi> for He paid <hi>tribute-mony</hi> by a Miracle: he had for <hi>needfull</hi> supply, but not for <hi>superfluity;</hi> and we conceive too, that what he had was <hi>given</hi> to him by such as <hi>loved</hi> him, and <hi>followed</hi> him, and <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistred</hi> to him of their <hi>substance,</hi> as <hi>Chusa, Herods</hi> stewards wife, and others, <hi>Luk.</hi> 8. 'tis not to be <hi>imagined</hi> that he, who wished <hi>others</hi> not to lay
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169782:6"/>up <hi>treasures</hi> for themselves <hi>on Earth,</hi> would him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self <hi>practice</hi> that which he <hi>disswaded</hi> others from. We know his speech concerning that <hi>rich</hi> yong man, how hard <hi>is it for a rich man to enter into the Kingdom of Heaven?</hi> But that we may finish <hi>in brief</hi> what we intend: We have seen how He, <hi>(vi.)</hi> Christ Jesus the Lord <hi>of life,</hi> and King of Kings, was pleased <hi>to content himself</hi> while he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst <hi>sinfull</hi> men on Earth; Not but that he could have had <hi>better</hi> provision; (for he deserved the best, and all had been <hi>too little,</hi> and far short of his <hi>deserts</hi>) yet as we have <hi>described</hi> his man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>diet, journeying</hi> and apparel, so it was; we come now to his Apostles.</p>
            <p>And they (Good Souls) were (after our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours Resurrection) so put to it, to <hi>Communicate</hi> their goods; for their Master, though he left them some <hi>spiritual</hi> Legacies, did not <hi>bequeath</hi> to any of them (no not to <hi>John that beloved Disciple</hi>) any <hi>temporal</hi> estate, or any Bishoprick, Deanary, Prebendary, nor Cardinalship, nor any <hi>mony</hi> to him or them, so that they were forc'd <hi>to break their bread from house to house,</hi> Acts 2.3. (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidently done) as to see none should (while the <hi>common store</hi> lasted) want; So also that there should be no <hi>mispending</hi> or profuse <hi>lavishing;</hi> means were short, for no question if their master, when he was <hi>taken,</hi> had had any store of <hi>Monies,</hi> or themselvs either, <hi>Judas</hi> would have <hi>discovered</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:169782:7"/>that; for he who did not spare to <hi>betray</hi> him, would not have made any <hi>scruple</hi> to have <hi>rob'd</hi> him, or them; with which, if <hi>he,</hi> or <hi>they</hi> had been <hi>furnished,</hi> it would have fallen to have been <hi>censured</hi> for <hi>lawfull</hi> pillage <hi>for the company</hi> who took him; and therefore we say it <hi>for truth,</hi> that <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> did speak truth, when they said, <hi>Silver and Gold have I none;</hi> they were not to carry a Scrip, because they should not put any thing into it. A cup of cold water and thanks. They plucked the Ears of corn for hunger, <hi>Act.</hi> 9. And <hi>Paul</hi> not only not coveted <hi>any mans Silver or Gold or Apparel,</hi> but justifies it, <hi>that these hands did administer to his necessities and to them that were with him;</hi> that <hi>he</hi> and the <hi>other</hi> Saints lived upon <hi>Collection,</hi> and peoples <hi>Charity,</hi> is plain if we please to see. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</p>
            <p>And he <hi>himself</hi> sayes <hi>of himself, as having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing;</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.10. Perswades the Corinthians to be liberall.</p>
            <p>And so the Galatians also; but <hi>perswades</hi> one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, does not <hi>constrain</hi> or <hi>force</hi> them; and yet he was <hi>content;</hi> and we see how he <hi>describes</hi> the Saints of God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. though famous men for <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Holiness,</hi> yet <hi>they wandered about in sheepskins, and Goatskins, being destitute, &amp;c.</hi> They were <hi>put so to it</hi> even for <hi>Lodging, Food</hi> and <hi>Ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and other <hi>Necessaries;</hi> these were <hi>so far</hi> from being <hi>provided</hi> for, that the <hi>Text</hi> saith, they
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:169782:7"/>were <hi>Destitute:</hi> And to shut up all, lets come,</p>
            <p>Fifthly, To speak briefly of the <hi>primitive</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, who lived in the first 300. years after Christ; how were they <hi>provided</hi> for? had they <hi>tythes</hi> paid them, or did they demand any such <hi>burthen</hi> to be laid upon the <hi>people</hi> of those times? Oh no! there were <hi>Cruces &amp; Patibula,</hi> Crosses and Gibbets, but little or no <hi>maintenance,</hi> and yet by them was the Gospel preached <hi>purely</hi> and <hi>powerfully; Aureos habebat tunc temporis Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesia pastores: They were golden Pastors</hi> for <hi>life</hi> and <hi>Doctrine, and yet lived</hi> upon <hi>the Charitable Collection of Believers;</hi> Yes, and that too was fain to be <hi>gathered</hi> and <hi>distributed</hi> privately a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst them; they had no <hi>Parsonage houses,</hi> or <hi>Glebe lands,</hi> nor scarce any good <hi>Countenance</hi> shewed to them, till <hi>Constantines</hi> time, and that <hi>lasted</hi> but a while neither; yet all this while as <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity</hi> and <hi>liberty</hi> was afforded to them, they <hi>did not cease</hi> to preach the Gospel of Christ, and to <hi>write</hi> rare and <hi>admirable</hi> pieces of Divinity: Much more here may and might be <hi>added,</hi> one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thus much for a <hi>ground work</hi> to what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows.</p>
            <p>And now O <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Ministers of <hi>England!</hi> do not take it ill, if we do what we can to <hi>you,</hi> as <hi>Andrew</hi> did to <hi>Peter</hi> his brother, <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.42. <hi>(viz.)</hi> of whom 'tis said, <hi>And he brought him to Jesus;</hi> dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169782:8"/>not, if the <hi>younger</hi> brother <hi>be in Christ</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you, and you be brought to Jesus Christ by <hi>your inferiors;</hi> to be short, slight not good councel, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>John</hi> 19.5. <hi>Behold the man!</hi> Do not do as the Prophet <hi>Isaiah</hi> saith, Esai. 53 <hi>Hide as it were your faces from him:</hi> and what! you shall find him <hi>on foot,</hi> who was the Master; will you <hi>his servants</hi> ride on <hi>pampered</hi> horses, as fatt as your selves; he had <hi>as much</hi> and more work <hi>to do,</hi> and but a <hi>short</hi> time to finish it in, and yet he did it perfectly, better than all you, and yet he travailed on foot; Leave off <hi>your superfluity</hi> in this kind, and what is <hi>vainly spent</hi> this way, may help for your provision.</p>
            <p>And secondly, for his Apparel. <hi>Behold the man!</hi> and blush at your <hi>pride</hi> &amp; variety in <hi>fashions,</hi> your costly clothes of <hi>Silks</hi> and <hi>Satins,</hi> and <hi>fine linnen</hi> from the crown of the Head to the sole of your Feet; Are <hi>you like him who came from Bosrah with garments all in blood?</hi> have ye <hi>yet as the Apostle sayes resisted to blood striving against sin?</hi> Heb. 12. get his Robes of Righteousness to cover your sins, or else <hi>all your wardrobes</hi> will prove but <hi>Rotten</hi> raggs; What say you to this conformity? We onely hint you.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, For his <hi>diet,</hi> twas <hi>sparing, charitable, frugal, seldom, homely</hi> and <hi>poor; Behold the man!</hi> Herein also, what shall be thought of your <hi>first</hi> and <hi>second</hi> courses? Eating, not <hi>Barley,</hi> but <hi>the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169782:8"/>purest</hi> wheat; Not to satiety, but too often <hi>to sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fet;</hi> who <hi>haunt</hi> feasts &amp; publike <hi>banquetings,</hi> desire to be called <hi>Rabbi, Doctor, good your worship, Reverend Sir,</hi> and taking the <hi>chief</hi> Seats, &amp;c. Your Master went but <hi>twice</hi> or <hi>thrice</hi> to feasts, to a Marriage in <hi>Cana</hi> of <hi>Galilee,</hi> and to <hi>Matthew</hi> the Publicans house; at the <hi>first</hi> and <hi>second</hi> he wrought a Miracle, to <hi>promote his fathers glory,</hi> and was admired for his <hi>heavenly</hi> discourse; but for your frequent feasts, we may say as <hi>Paul</hi> to the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians, <hi>Ye come together for the worse and not the better, shall I praise you for this, I praise you not.</hi> 1 Cor. 11.24, 25.</p>
            <p>And for Monies he had <hi>little</hi> or <hi>none,</hi> onely for <hi>necessity;</hi> if we should <hi>speak</hi> home, and why not? what becomes of the 300. and 400. l. <hi>per annum?</hi> Do you put it into <hi>bags</hi> that have <hi>seven holes?</hi> do you not grieve there are no more <hi>fat morsels</hi> for your large stomachs? You would <hi>well</hi> be content with pluralities, and those <hi>no little ones,</hi> nay <hi>totquots</hi> would down with you too, (if allowed by the State) <hi>is this, to be joyned to the Lord, and to be one Spirit?</hi> 2 Cor. 2. to take and <hi>command</hi> tythes, is that to live as Christ did? or to be conformable to him?</p>
            <p>And now to come <hi>to try you</hi> by the Apostles and primitive Christians, was not, what is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <hi>of them,</hi> written for our instruction? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. Could we but find <hi>any of you</hi> who pretend
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169782:9"/>such <hi>holiness,</hi> and seem to be such <hi>Reformed</hi> Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, to be <hi>true followers</hi> of them, as <hi>they were</hi> of Christ: <hi>Follow me</hi> (says the Apostle <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>even as I follow Christ.</hi> And Christ says, <hi>follow me;</hi> but how <hi>slowly</hi> and <hi>indirectly,</hi> if at all do you follow, nay, do not you go clean contrary to him and them also? if we should <hi>Anatomize</hi> your <hi>Actions,</hi> we should find you <hi>others</hi> than you <hi>seem</hi> for, but if you be <hi>false,</hi> you know <hi>your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward;</hi> We will not <hi>stain</hi> our paper, with opening your diseases, <hi>your own sin will find you out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We <hi>press</hi> this to you, that it is <hi>not fitting</hi> you should live <hi>unjustly</hi> by Tythes, and of other mens Goods, and Command them, <hi>with rigor</hi> too; but <hi>indeavor to have</hi> your Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance by the peoples <hi>Good will,</hi> and <hi>blessing,</hi> and <hi>Charitable Collections,</hi> for <hi>they</hi> will bring you <hi>peace</hi> at the last: To sum up all therefore,</p>
            <p>First, That though this point of <hi>Reduction</hi> and <hi>Apostolical</hi> and <hi>Primitive</hi> Reformation, be to <hi>Carnal</hi> Ministers and others, <hi>Hard</hi> and <hi>Odious,</hi> perhaps though without just cause, yet <hi>in it self,</hi> being <hi>essentially</hi> and <hi>simply</hi> true, 'tis not to be <hi>slighted</hi> but <hi>followed</hi> and <hi>imbraced.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Though it be <hi>hard,</hi> especially to <hi>flesh</hi> and <hi>blood,</hi> yet Ministers <hi>above all others,</hi> ought not <hi>to consult</hi> with them; but, as it is <hi>true,</hi> so it hath been <hi>practised</hi> by the best with <hi>Approbation</hi> and <hi>content,</hi> even by Christ, his Apostles, and the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:169782:9"/>
               <hi>Primitive</hi> Christians, and therefore not onely <hi>possible,</hi> but fitting to be <hi>renewed</hi> and <hi>established.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, As 'tis <hi>true,</hi> and hath been practised by <hi>the best,</hi> so 'tis the <hi>Ancientest, Freest,</hi> most <hi>Equal, Safest, Comfortablest,</hi> and most <hi>Satisfactory</hi> way for Ministers <hi>Maintenance;</hi> therefore having <hi>Truth, Practice, Antiquity, Freedom, Equity, Safety, Comfort</hi> and <hi>Satisfaction</hi> in it, ought to be <hi>a Pattern, President, Rule</hi> and <hi>Example for Maintenance</hi> for Ministers <hi>now,</hi> as well as <hi>then;</hi> for our Ministers as well <hi>as those</hi> who have been <hi>before</hi> them, whose <hi>Labor</hi> and <hi>Learning</hi> was <hi>no less,</hi> and whose <hi>Piety</hi> did <hi>exceed</hi> ours, and yet they were <hi>thankfull</hi> and <hi>content</hi> for such <hi>Collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and why not <hi>ours</hi> too? This <hi>way</hi> of <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance</hi> will <hi>try their Spirits,</hi> whether they got into this <hi>Function</hi> or <hi>Imployment,</hi> more for <hi>Love,</hi> or <hi>the Loaves</hi> they get by it; for our parts, they, who will not <hi>be content</hi> with it, should be <hi>content</hi> without it; from hence will <hi>issue</hi> two Querees to be <hi>resolved,</hi> to help <hi>forward</hi> this Action.</p>
            <div type="questions">
               <p>1. <hi>Who shall Collect it,</hi> when <hi>and</hi> where <hi>to be done?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. <hi>How to be</hi> distributed?</p>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Answer.</head>
                  <p>IN every <hi>Hundred,</hi> according to the number of <hi>Parishes</hi> therein, <hi>Greater</hi> or <hi>Lesser;</hi> Let two
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:169782:10"/>or three <hi>Godly, able, well affected,</hi> well <hi>Reputed,</hi> and <hi>Conscionable</hi> men in <hi>each</hi> Parish be <hi>chosen,</hi> and let them <hi>Collect carefully, quietly,</hi> and meekly <hi>the Charity</hi> of each <hi>Inhabitant,</hi> and <hi>others,</hi> upon the first Lords day of the month, or upon any within the moneth (as they shall find <hi>fittest,</hi>) and if any <hi>Inhabitant</hi> be <hi>absent,</hi> to repair to their <hi>houses,</hi> or to note <hi>him</hi> or <hi>them</hi> with a blank, that so <hi>he</hi> or <hi>they</hi> may double next <hi>Collection,</hi> or add some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to it; let each <hi>Inhabitants</hi> gift be set upon his name, with the <hi>Moneth</hi> wherein Collected; and let the benefit of all the <hi>Gleab-Lands</hi> in each Hundred be <hi>equally</hi> liable to the <hi>advancing</hi> this Collection in general, and to the helping <hi>the lesser</hi> and poorer <hi>Parishes;</hi> for <hi>Impropriators</hi> being <hi>satisfied,</hi> the <hi>Gleab-Lands</hi> will much aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ease the Collection.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="question">
                  <p>2. <hi>How to be distributed?</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>Answer.</head>
                  <p>EQually, to all the Ministers <hi>alike,</hi> according as our Saviour speaks in that parable <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.2. The Master gave <hi>to every labourer</hi> a penny; not a <hi>pound</hi> to one, and but a <hi>penny</hi> to another; but the Text saith, and <hi>every one</hi> received a <hi>penny;</hi> some did (as perhaps some of our Ministers will do now at this <hi>equality</hi> of Distribution) <hi>grudge</hi> and <hi>murmure;</hi> but the Act <hi>of Equality</hi> was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:169782:10"/>proved then by our Saviour Christ, and therefore not to be <hi>thought amiss</hi> of now; Since he <hi>equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> it, why should <hi>any</hi> go about, or <hi>desire</hi> to have <hi>more</hi> than his <hi>fellow</hi> Labourer? So that the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister of one <hi>place</hi> shall partake equally of the <hi>Collection</hi> so made, as another; if any <hi>Believer</hi> or Charitable <hi>minded</hi> man please to do any thing <hi>in private,</hi> thats left to his own <hi>free</hi> choice, as God shall <hi>move</hi> his heart, or as he <hi>finds</hi> that he <hi>reaps</hi> benefit by the hearing of Gods word; a mans <hi>private</hi> Charity is <hi>free:</hi> Yet we would not that any should make that <hi>an excuse</hi> for not <hi>giving</hi> to the publike Collection.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>due</hi> and equal <hi>Distribution</hi> to all the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters alike, we conceive, will <hi>encourage</hi> all <hi>alike,</hi> and cause every respective Minister in his <hi>Calling</hi> to be <hi>painfull</hi> and <hi>Industrious,</hi> to live <hi>quiet</hi> and <hi>loving</hi> with and amongst his <hi>Parishioners,</hi> and to keep <hi>all of them</hi> from <hi>Envy</hi> and <hi>Hatred.</hi> The labour <hi>in gathering,</hi> and proportionating it for <hi>each</hi> Minister, is easie, and may be <hi>performed</hi> with loss of <hi>little</hi> time, and may be <hi>the willinger</hi> born, because <hi>this</hi> doth free them from Tythe pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; Let the respective <hi>portions,</hi> when <hi>summ'd up</hi> and <hi>divided,</hi> be brought to the <hi>several</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters to <hi>their</hi> houses, with a certificate under <hi>six,</hi> or <hi>more</hi> of the Collectors hands, in Testimony of the truth; and 'tis fitting that <hi>one</hi> of them, in each Parish, <hi>so chosen</hi> for Collectors, should be <hi>able</hi> to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:169782:11"/>write what is Collected; the <hi>poor</hi> and <hi>Impotent</hi> are to be had regard unto, and though they do not give, yet if Pious, and fit to be members of the Church of Christ; Not to be debarred any of the Ordinances of the Gospel.</p>
                  <p>And this <hi>Collection</hi> being practised, let <hi>all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> of Church-dues (so called) and all <hi>Tythes,</hi> great and small, and offerings whatsoever, be <hi>forthwith</hi> abolished.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>—Addatur, si quid novistis rectius, istis.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>And with <hi>this Collection,</hi> and the Gleab-Lands added to it, the Ministers we hope may rest con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented; there are other wayes proposeable, if this <hi>seems</hi> too <hi>mean</hi> for their high Spirits.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="example">
                  <head>Example.</head>
                  <p>IF all the Freehold, and Copy-hold Lands in <hi>England</hi> will make up 200000. times a 100. l. <hi>per annum,</hi> and let every 100. l. be proportioned to pay 5. l. the yeer to the Minister, every 50. l. pay yeerly 50. s. 20. l. 20. s. 10. l. 10. s. and so propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionably for the <hi>least</hi> as well as <hi>the greatest,</hi> which is but after 12. d. in the pound. We say then that this number <hi>will maintain</hi> 10000. Ministers, and every Minister shall have an 100. l. <hi>per annum,</hi> and yet there will be 200000. l. more than needs, if there be not 8000. Ministers in the Land, as <hi>'tis thought</hi> there are not; and <hi>out of this</hi> we would have the Widdows of Ministers to be allowed
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:169782:11"/>50. l. for to keep them in their old age, when their husbands are <hi>dead, or else to be for, and in stead of the first fruits office,</hi> if that be yet kept up; and <hi>to help</hi> to pay off the Impropriators, it will (we conceive) <hi>perform</hi> all these; and yet, what <hi>Freeholder</hi> and <hi>Copy-holder,</hi> doth not pay <hi>treble,</hi> nay <hi>more</hi> than so, as they pay Tythes; and (we believe) neither of them will <hi>grudge</hi> to pay after this <hi>allowance</hi> of 12. d. in the pound, which yet will be <hi>a good allowance</hi> for each Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster; and this may be done with ease. Or let the Ministers themselves (if they can) <hi>find out</hi> a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>surer</hi> or <hi>equaller</hi> way; without doubt <hi>twill</hi> be imbraced; for we are not so far <hi>wedded</hi> to our own <hi>judgements,</hi> but we will and can easily <hi>forgo</hi> ours, and subscribe <hi>to better,</hi> so the work be done; This obstacle of Tyth-taking being once <hi>removd,</hi> the people will <hi>in love</hi> embrace their Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, <hi>Ʋnity</hi> and <hi>Amity</hi> will be on all sides, and <hi>ease</hi> and <hi>comfort</hi> to the Ministers in their <hi>Imployments.</hi> We hope to see it effected to Gods Glory, and <hi>every mans</hi> ease, <hi>contentment</hi> and satisfaction.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="resolution">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:169782:12"/>
               <head>2. <hi>How</hi> Impropriators <hi>may be</hi> satisfied? <hi>Resolved.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere are but these two things that <hi>hinder</hi> the removing of Tythes, <hi>(viz.)</hi> a <hi>Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance</hi> for the Ministers, and the <hi>satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying</hi> the Impropriators; we have <hi>indeavoured,</hi> and have (we hope) <hi>found out</hi> and laid down a <hi>way</hi> of <hi>livelyhood</hi> and <hi>Maintenance</hi> for the first of these; <hi>the Ministers of England (viz.)</hi> either by way of <hi>publike</hi> Collection, or else by <hi>a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> out of all <hi>Free-hold,</hi> and <hi>Copy hold</hi> Lands, by which <hi>provision</hi> 'tis concluded, that as there shall be <hi>no</hi> preferring one Minister before another, or allowing <hi>more</hi> to one than to another, so tis <hi>pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently</hi> fore-cast, that <hi>none</hi> shall want a <hi>good</hi> and <hi>sufficient</hi> maintenance; There remains the second of these questions to be <hi>resolved, (viz.)</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>How the Impropriators may be satisfied?</head>
                  <p>These men we <hi>know,</hi> or <hi>hope,</hi> will <hi>blush</hi> to say, as the Ministers, that if Tythes be put down they are undone, and know not how to live, for <hi>'tis known</hi> sufficiently that these, <hi>the Impropriators,</hi> have had a sweet time of gathering, and may say, as 'tis in the Gospel, <hi>We have goods laid up for many years, Soul take thine ease:</hi> and though there
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:169782:12"/>be already <hi>sufficient</hi> Arguments to <hi>convince</hi> them, set forth in Print concerning their <hi>tenure</hi> and <hi>practice;</hi> Yet <hi>to drive the Nail home</hi> (as we use to say) and to make <hi>sure work</hi> of the business, that the <hi>mouths</hi> of the <hi>Gainsayers</hi> may be stopped <hi>for time to come,</hi> we say to this <hi>point</hi> further; And first.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Ab Injusto.</head>
                  <p>Their very <hi>Tenure</hi> and <hi>Purchase,</hi> much more <hi>their Practice</hi> and <hi>Execution</hi> of it, <hi>to extremity,</hi> is <hi>simply</hi> unjust and unfitting; the more <hi>Ancient</hi> it is, and the <hi>longer</hi> they have <hi>lived</hi> by that course, <hi>so much the worse;</hi> Nay more, should we say <hi>that the very Act</hi> of <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, who did <hi>pull down</hi> the Abbies, and destroy <hi>divers,</hi> if not <hi>all</hi> the <hi>then</hi> called and reputed <hi>houses of Religion,</hi> though nothing so, not out of any <hi>zeal</hi> he had to the <hi>pure</hi> Preaching of Gods Word, or for the suppression of <hi>Popery</hi> or <hi>Popish Superstition,</hi> no nor yet for the gross <hi>misdemeanors</hi> and <hi>abuses</hi> that were in the Abbots, Monks, or Friars of those times, though they did <hi>abound,</hi> as he knew well enough; but he did it, either <hi>to enrich</hi> his own <hi>Coffers</hi> by others ruine, or else to <hi>please, supply,</hi> or <hi>satisfie</hi> some of his <hi>old</hi> Courtiers, or to help <hi>towards the charges</hi> of his Wars in <hi>France,</hi> or for that the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy <hi>were then</hi> in the <hi>Premunire;</hi> but Chiefly <hi>to be revenged</hi> upon them and their father the Pope, for <hi>not yeilding</hi> to the satisfying of his desires, concerning <hi>his Marriage</hi> with the Lady <hi>Catha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine,</hi>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:169782:13"/>his Brother <hi>Arthurs</hi> Widdow: who, as a Maiden, and as <hi>his brothers wife,</hi> and <hi>as a Widdow</hi> was virtuous, onely as she became <hi>his wife</hi> was faulty; yet should we say that this Act of his (as his) (though God did use him as his Instrument in it to abolish Popery and Idolatry yet it was not the Kings intent, thought or desire to do so,) was <hi>unjust</hi> having no surer Warrant for the upholding <hi>its legality,</hi> but <hi>his</hi> Power and will, <hi>his</hi> covetous mind, and Tyrannical Oppression, <hi>his cruelty</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst his own Subjects, and <hi>desire of Revenge,</hi> we should but (as we conceive) speak <hi>truth;</hi> and if so, consider this, you who are made <hi>Rich</hi> and <hi>Fat,</hi> and <hi>great</hi> by this means, how <hi>the Petitioning for these means</hi> by your Ancestors, or yet how the <hi>undervalued</hi> purchase of them, from such an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull ground, can <hi>all these years</hi> be held and yet continued for <hi>good</hi> and <hi>conscionable,</hi> and <hi>just</hi> before God or <hi>good</hi> men by you their heirs, <hi>professing</hi> the purity of Religion: and for certain, any one that hath eyes and judgement may see, and say, that if the Act of that King was in any kind (though Accidentally <hi>equal</hi> in the <hi>suppressing</hi> the houses, and taking their means) 'twas because <hi>they did abuse them,</hi> and misapply them to <hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>superstition,</hi> to gluttony, if not to whoredom, and such other sins. May we not definitively say, (or why we in after times bound to his Act, when as 'tis found to be ill grounded, and full of Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies)
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:169782:13"/>That it is but a <hi>conscionable</hi> and <hi>just</hi> Act, if now, <hi>the same means</hi> (though in other hands) be as <hi>grosly</hi> abused <hi>to Pride</hi> and <hi>Ambition,</hi> to <hi>Extortion, Covetousness, Ʋsury, to Glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony, drunkenness,</hi> and to <hi>extream</hi> uncharitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, it is <hi>for certain</hi> but so, if our Parliament <hi>by way of Reformation</hi> cause the means <hi>te return,</hi> and for ever <hi>to remain</hi> to the <hi>right</hi> owners, (we mean <hi>the husbandmen</hi> of <hi>England</hi>) <hi>out of whose labours,</hi> and <hi>stocks</hi> these <hi>Creatures,</hi> called Impropriators, do live so wantonly and Lordly; and <hi>if they</hi> be so <hi>setled upon their Lees,</hi> that they will be <hi>unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> to be stirred; Why, So <hi>we know</hi> the Abbots and Friars, and Nunnes <hi>were much agrieved</hi> to be turned out of doors, and stript of their means; <hi>to which yet</hi> they had <hi>a surer title</hi> than our Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priators have, yet 'twas <hi>done,</hi> and done <hi>to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose,</hi> and why not now?</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Let our Impropriators <hi>set before their eyes</hi> the practical <hi>justice</hi> and <hi>discretion,</hi> and Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableness of the Parliament, and let them imitate their Actions; who knows not but that at the beginning of these Wars many <hi>Patrons</hi> and <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons</hi> left their <hi>places</hi> and <hi>revenews,</hi> and took them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves <hi>to Arms</hi> Actually against the Parliament, and the reupon the Parliament wisely did (and <hi>justly they might</hi>) sequester such Lordships &amp; Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonages <hi>into their hands</hi> for the good of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth; yet they did not <hi>hold them for ever,</hi>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:169782:14"/>nor cut off <hi>the Heirs</hi> of such Lordships, (if not against them) no nor yet <hi>their fathers</hi> from <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possessing</hi> them, upon their <hi>due</hi> submission, and <hi>laying down of Arms;</hi> no nor yet <hi>did they</hi> (though they neither wanted <hi>power,</hi> nor <hi>sufficient</hi> cause) keep the Parsonages <hi>sequestred</hi> in their own hands, but <hi>as fast,</hi> and <hi>assoon</hi> as Ministers could be <hi>provided</hi> for them, did freely place them in, and bestowed them, that so Gods word might be preached in such parishes again.</p>
                  <p>Behold (we pray) Oh Impropriators, and <hi>shut not</hi> your eyes hereat! What <hi>a Mass</hi> of Wealth would have <hi>come in</hi> to the Publike by this means, and <hi>how justly</hi> might it have been <hi>performed,</hi> and yet the Parliament <hi>used it not,</hi> but hath <hi>disposed them</hi> to good uses, and to the <hi>right</hi> Owners a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; <hi>go ye and do so likewise;</hi> and 'tis time, you having gotten great Estates to your selves already by this way, and you will have <hi>praise</hi> and <hi>love of all men,</hi> and will enjoy the <hi>quiet</hi> and <hi>peace</hi> of a <hi>good</hi> Conscience.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, To <hi>satisfie</hi> you, we say: 'tis not what you will <hi>demand,</hi> or what you <hi>would</hi> have to <hi>sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render,</hi> but what you <hi>ought to have;</hi> men are not to look <hi>so much</hi> upon their own covetous desires, as upon <hi>what's equal</hi> and just. Hereupon we say, and do for the most part, in most places <hi>find,</hi> that the very Glebe-Lands belonging to the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonages so impropriated,</hi> if made <hi>sure</hi> to you and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:169782:14"/>yours, as <hi>Free soccage,</hi> those Lands being in some <hi>places</hi> very large, (as of 200. l. 150. l. 100. l. 80. l. or 60 l. <hi>per annum,</hi>) will <hi>satisfie</hi> and <hi>equal,</hi> if not <hi>surpass</hi> your Monies <hi>disbursed,</hi> for your Purchase; especially having not onely <hi>had them,</hi> but Tythes <hi>besides</hi> payd to you along time together, and your Ancestors and your selves having had (as tis in the proverb) <hi>Robin hoods penny worth</hi> in the first Purchase.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, You cannot receive <hi>any comfort</hi> in the holding up Tythes; for, <hi>Non fuit sic ab initio, 'twas not so from the beginning,</hi> but 'tis <hi>continued</hi> as our Saviour says (in another case) <hi>through the hardness of your hearts;</hi> as <hi>Moses</hi> permitted them, <hi>so now</hi> Tythes are <hi>permissively,</hi> not <hi>Authoritatively</hi> yours: 'tis <hi>with you</hi> as tis with Usurers, <hi>permitted</hi> not <hi>allowed:</hi> yet, they have <hi>a propriety</hi> to, and in <hi>their Monies,</hi> you <hi>not so</hi> unto Tythes: the very <hi>Brand</hi> and <hi>Name</hi> of your <hi>Parsonages</hi> shew, that you are <hi>not they</hi> that should <hi>hold</hi> them; <hi>Impropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> improperly <hi>yours;</hi> here's <hi>no Propriety:</hi> thus <hi>in the name</hi> is engraven <hi>the shame</hi> of such as hold them; <hi>Improper,</hi> in all respects; <hi>Improper,</hi> in a well ordered Comōn-wealth; <hi>Improper,</hi> for their Own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to receive; and <hi>as Improper</hi> for others to pay.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, It is <hi>a fearfull case</hi> to live in such a way, as is <hi>obstructive</hi> to a <hi>godly</hi> Reformation; to have <hi>a mans wealth by such an Indirect course,</hi> as to be <hi>a stumbling block</hi> to hinder a general good, is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:169782:15"/>
                     <hi>lamentable;</hi> You cannot but <hi>hear</hi> and know, <hi>that every man is against you, and you against every man.</hi> Covet not <hi>that</hi> which is <hi>not yours;</hi> since <hi>you do not labour,</hi> how come you <hi>to reap?</hi> 'tis true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, he that <hi>sows</hi> should <hi>reap,</hi> but not he <hi>that sows not.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Lastly, All this <hi>being true,</hi> and said <hi>to awaken</hi> our Impropriators, let them <hi>beware</hi> how they longer <hi>go on</hi> against the <hi>light of Conscience</hi> and <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge;</hi> We intend <hi>not to force</hi> them, but <hi>to perswade</hi> them; we hope they will not be <hi>unperswasible</hi> in this particular. Let them <hi>exhibite</hi> and shew <hi>their lawfulness,</hi> we say <hi>their lawfulness</hi> to take Tythes, and we have done: if they have a Right, <hi>produce it</hi> to the world; or if they have not, let them <hi>be willing</hi> to take <hi>a fair</hi> satisfaction at their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threns hands, to avoid <hi>further</hi> trouble, and <hi>inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table</hi> scandal to the people of God.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Rules for the helping forward the satisfaction of Impropriators.</head>
                  <p>1. Let their Number <hi>be computed</hi> through <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>2. Their just value, how <hi>let</hi> or <hi>sett.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>3. How long <hi>purchased,</hi> and <hi>from</hi> whom.</p>
                  <p>4. What given <hi>justly,</hi> when <hi>purchased.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>5. They may be allowed four yeers <hi>purchase</hi> for their Tythes, and have <hi>their Gleabe-lands</hi> for
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:169782:15"/>ever to themselves and heirs; which admit an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriation be worth 500. l. <hi>per annum,</hi> having a 100. l. <hi>per annum</hi> of Glebe-Lands; there will be to be paid for four yeers for tythes 1600. l. which <hi>summ,</hi> with the <hi>Glebe,</hi> will pay most, if not all the Impropriators off proportionably. And if there be <hi>in all England</hi> 2000. Impropriate Livings, and one with another valued at 200. <hi>per annum,</hi> to buy off these at four veers Purchase, will <hi>amount</hi> unto the summ of 1600000. l. which is <hi>one million</hi> and <hi>six hundred thousand pound</hi> Sterling; and yet the Impropriators shall have their <hi>Gleabe Lands,</hi> but they are to joyn <hi>with the other</hi> Free-holders, and Copy-holders, <hi>towards the payment</hi> of the severall Ministers afterwards.</p>
                  <p>This may be <hi>Collected</hi> by way of <hi>Taxe,</hi> and no Free-holders, or Copy-holders, specially when as their <hi>uncertain fines</hi> and <hi>Harriots</hi> are taken off, will except against the payment of <hi>their shares,</hi> nor (we hope) any of the Impropriators rest <hi>unsatisfied;</hi> they bearing no share in this said <hi>Taxe</hi> of 1600000. l. and this will in one year and four Months be paid off to the Impropriators, after a Rate of 100000. l. <hi>per Mensem</hi> through <hi>England;</hi> and Tythes immediately to Cease.</p>
                  <trailer>Finis esto Decimarum.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>